<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>com.bilingify.readest</id>

  <name>Readest</name>
  <summary>Modern, feature-rich ebook reader</summary>

  <description>
    <p>Readest is a modern, feature-rich ebook reader designed for avid readers offering seamless cross-platform access, powerful tools, and an intuitive interface to elevate your reading experience.</p>
    <p>Built as a modern rewrite of Foliate, Readest leverages Next.js 15 and Tauri v2 to deliver a smooth, cross-platform experience across macOS, Windows, Linux, Android, iOS, and the Web.</p>
    <p>Whether you're analyzing complex texts, immersing yourself in stories, or exploring new ideas, Readest adapts to your needs with powerful features for deep, thoughtful reading.</p>
    <p>Key features include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Multi-format support for EPUB, MOBI, KF8 (AZW3), FB2, CBZ, TXT, and PDF (experimental).</li>
      <li>Switch between scrolling or paginated reading modes for your preferred reading style.</li>
      <li>Full-text search across the entire book to find relevant sections quickly.</li>
      <li>Add highlights, bookmarks, and notes to enhance your reading experience and learning.</li>
      <li>Easily excerpt text from books for detailed notes and analysis.</li>
      <li>Instantly look up words and terms with built-in dictionary and Wikipedia integration.</li>
      <li>Translate selected text instantly using DeepL for accurate translations.</li>
      <li>Parallel Reading: Read two books or documents simultaneously in a split-screen view, perfect for researchers, language learners, and multitaskers.</li>
      <li>Customize fonts, layout, theme mode, and theme colors for a personalized reading experience.</li>
      <li>Cross-platform synchronization of book files, reading progress, notes, and bookmarks across all supported platforms.</li>
      <li>Text-to-Speech functionality for a more accessible reading experience.</li>
      <li>Organize, sort, and manage your entire ebook library with advanced library management tools.</li>
      <li>One-click file association to quickly open files in Readest from your file browser.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Readest also includes custom CSS support for personalized styling, and code syntax highlighting for technical books. The application is designed to honor the legacy of deep reading while embracing modern technology for an enhanced experience.</p>
  </description>

  <categories>
    <category>Office</category>
    <category>Education</category>
    <category>Literature</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword translate="no">readest</keyword>
    <keyword>ebook</keyword>
    <keyword>reader</keyword>
    <keyword>epub</keyword>
    <keyword>mobi</keyword>
    <keyword>pdf</keyword>
    <keyword>reading</keyword>
    <keyword>books</keyword>
    <keyword>annotation</keyword>
    <keyword>highlight</keyword>
    <keyword>notes</keyword>
    <keyword>translation</keyword>
    <keyword>tts</keyword>
    <keyword>sync</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/readest/readest</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/readest/readest/issues</url>
  <url type="help">https://github.com/readest/readest/wiki</url>
  <url type="donation">https://github.com/sponsors/readest</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/readest/readest</url>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">com.bilingify.readest.desktop</launchable>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.10.6" date="2026-04-13">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Library: Much faster browsing for large collections</li>
          <li>Reading: Added an option to keep the book's original paragraph layout</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed page navigation for Arabic books</li>
          <li>PDF: Fixed TTS reading interruptions at line breaks in PDFs</li>
          <li>PDF: You can now apply your chosen theme colors to PDFs</li>
          <li>Sync: Added HTTP Basic auth support for CWA</li>
          <li>Sync: Improved progress sync with Hardcover.app</li>
          <li>OPDS: You can now edit your registered catalogs, with better handling of download filenames</li>
          <li>Speed Reading: Your reading position now syncs across devices</li>
          <li>Platform: Fixed window buttons on macOS, reduced crashes on iOS</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.10.4" date="2026-04-06">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Annotations: You can now name your highlight colors, and your custom names sync across devices</li>
          <li>Annotations: Fixed highlights that stayed on the page after being deleted from the sidebar</li>
          <li>Speed Reading: Added an option to split long words, a faster countdown</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Fixed double playback when tapping the play button in quick succession</li>
          <li>Accessibility: Dropdown menus now open reliably when activated with the keyboard</li>
          <li>Reading: Background textures now display correctly when you override the theme background color</li>
          <li>Translation: Temporarily disabled the Yandex provider while its service is unavailable</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.10.2" date="2026-04-05">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Reading: Added single section scroll option, keyboard shortcuts help dialog, and reading ruler improvements</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed Adobe font deobfuscation and applied theme colors to PDFs</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed paginator freeze, image sizing on resize, and vertical writing mode compatibility</li>
          <li>Annotations: Fixed annotations grouped under wrong chapter and added highlight opacity setting</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Added dedicated TTS settings tab with highlight opacity and keyboard shortcuts for navigation</li>
          <li>Sync: Added Hardcover.app sync integration and improved KOSync progress accuracy</li>
          <li>KOReader Plugin: Added full annotation sync option and fixed sync-related crashes</li>
          <li>OPDS: Added custom catalog headers with web proxy consent and fixed feed display issues</li>
          <li>Speed Reading: Added per-chapter progress bar and speed selector dropdown</li>
          <li>Android: Added D-pad navigation for Android TV remote controller</li>
          <li>Theme: Added atmosphere Easter egg with video overlay and ambient audio</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.10.1" date="2026-03-22">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Reading: Added continuous scroll and spread layout support for EPUBs</li>
          <li>Reading: Added current time and battery display in footer</li>
          <li>Reading: Added TTS, annotation support, pinch-to-zoom, and scroll mode for PDFs</li>
          <li>Library: Added backup/restore to a zip file and batch metadata refresh</li>
          <li>KOReader: Added bookmark and annotation sync between KOReader and Readest devices</li>
          <li>Footnotes: Added back navigation with link history and more responsive popup sizing</li>
          <li>Annotations: Added loupe display when selecting text in instant annotation mode</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Fixed TTS reading position tracking in scrolled mode</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.101" date="2026-02-28">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Fixed an issue where TTS could not continue to the next chapter</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed an issue importing very large TXT files on iOS</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed the layout of the reading ruler in scrolled mode</li>
          <li>Reading: Smoother page-turn animations for a more fluid experience</li>
          <li>Reading: Added a gallery mode to zoom and browse images within books</li>
          <li>Annotations: Page numbers are now displayed and exported with highlights and notes</li>
          <li>Annotations: Added support for exporting highlights to Readwise</li>
          <li>OPDS: Fixed missing book descriptions in OPDS feeds</li>
          <li>Android: Improved compatibility with older WebView versions on Android</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.100" date="2026-02-13">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Automatically moves to the next chapter when the current chapter finishes</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed the reading ruler on Android</li>
          <li>Reading: Improved RSVP layout and stability</li>
          <li>Reading: Fixed an issue where some EPUB books could not adjust font size</li>
          <li>Annotations: Added a magnifier (loupe) when adjusting text selection</li>
          <li>Annotations: Text selection now snaps to word boundaries for better accuracy</li>
          <li>Annotations: Custom highlight colors now apply correctly in the sidebar</li>
          <li>Dictionary: Added a back button for easier navigation</li>
          <li>Dictionary: Fixed an issue where Dictionary and Wikipedia could not open on Android</li>
          <li>Metadata: Added collapsible sections in Book Details</li>
          <li>Metadata: Added support for parsing series information from Calibre-exported EPUB files</li>
          <li>Eink: Improved component layout and colors in E-ink mode</li>
          <li>Layout: Sidebar toggle button position is now persistent</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.99" date="2026-02-07">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Reading: Added a reading ruler (line highlight) to help guide your eyes while reading</li>
          <li>Reading: Added paragraph-by-paragraph reading mode for more focused navigation</li>
          <li>Reading: Added a speed reading mode to support faster reading workflows</li>
          <li>Reading: Added support for gamepad input to turn pages</li>
          <li>Accessibility: Improved TalkBack support in dropdown menus for smoother navigation</li>
          <li>Accessibility: Page navigation buttons are now always visible to screen readers</li>
          <li>Accessibility: Reading progress is now updated correctly when navigating with screen readers</li>
          <li>Annotations: Expanded highlight customization with more color options</li>
          <li>Annotations: Added an option to export annotations as plain text</li>
          <li>Library: Added grouping by author and series for better library organization</li>
          <li>Library: Added support of marking books as finished</li>
          <li>Search: Added fuzzy search to quickly find settings even with partial keywords</li>
          <li>Table of Contents: Added page numbers for nested TOC entries</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Added navigation controls to return to the current reading position</li>
          <li>Linux: Added an in-app updater for AppImage builds</li>
          <li>E-ink: Improved color support for color E-ink devices to display richer highlights</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.98" date="2026-01-21">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Bookshelf: Added the ability to export original book files directly from the book details dialog</li>
          <li>Bookshelf: Added a new sorting option to organize books by publish date</li>
          <li>Bookshelf: Improved performance for large library with faster and more stable imports</li>
          <li>OPDS: Improved download reliability by correctly detecting filenames for PDF and CBZ files</li>
          <li>Proofreading: Added support for whole-word replacement to make text corrections more precise</li>
          <li>Notes: Added the ability to export notes using a customizable template</li>
          <li>PDF: Added support for panning within PDF documents for easier navigation</li>
          <li>PDF: Improved performance by pre-rendering the next page for smoother page transitions</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Added support for word replacement to improve pronunciation during playback</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Fixed an issue where playback speed settings were not applied correctly on Linux</li>
          <li>E-ink: Improved reading stability by preventing unwanted scrolling when animations are disabled or on e-ink devices</li>
          <li>Discord: Added Discord Rich Presence to display your current reading status on Desktop platforms</li>
          <li>Android: Fixed an issue that could cause occasional crashes during app startup</li>
          <li>Fonts: Improved web font loading for faster and more stable text rendering</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.97" date="2026-01-10">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>Annotations: Added annotation bubble icons directly on text with instant note popups</li>
          <li>Annotations: Enabled quick highlighting when selecting text</li>
          <li>Annotations: Added the ability to edit the text range of existing highlights</li>
          <li>Annotations: Added an annotation navigation bar for easier browsing</li>
          <li>OPDS: Fixed an issue where CBZ files could not be downloaded from OPDS catalogs</li>
          <li>OPDS: Improved compatibility with Komga OPDS servers</li>
          <li>OPDS: Added support for OPDS servers using self-signed SSL certificates</li>
          <li>PDF: Fixed an issue where some PDF files failed to open</li>
          <li>E-ink: Optimized colors and layout for improved e-ink device readability</li>
          <li>Search: Added search term history for quicker repeated searches</li>
          <li>Text-to-Speech: Reduced excessive pauses between sentences for smoother playback</li>
          <li>File Transfer: Introduced a background transfer queue for uploading and downloading books</li>
          <li>Proofreading: Added a proofread tool that can replace text directly within books</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.96" date="2025-12-19">
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>TTS: Resolved an issue where Edge TTS was blocked in certain regions</li>
          <li>OPDS: Improved compatibility with older versions of Calibre Web</li>
          <li>OPDS: Added an instant search bar for faster browsing in OPDS catalogs</li>
          <li>OPDS: Added a curated book catalog from Standard Ebooks</li>
          <li>Bookshelf: Added a “Group Books” action to the context menu</li>
          <li>Comics: Fixed layout issues to improve comic book reading</li>
          <li>Layout: Footnote popups now adapt correctly to different screen sizes</li>
          <li>Layout: Fixed an issue where the maximum inline width was not applied to EPUBs</li>
          <li>Sync: Improved file downloading by correctly handling special characters in filenames</li>
          <li>UI: Added an option to temporarily dismiss the reading progress bar</li>
          <li>Settings: Screen brightness adjustments now apply only to the reader view</li>
          <li>iOS: You can now open files directly in Readest from the Files app</li>
          <li>macOS: Added a global menu option to open files with Readest</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>

  <metadata_license>FSFAP</metadata_license>
  <project_license>AGPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>

  <developer id="com.readest">
    <name>Readest Team</name>
  </developer>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Readest main interface with annotation</caption>
      <image type="source">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/readest/readest/refs/heads/main/data/screenshots/annotations.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Reading interface with dark mode</caption>
      <image type="source">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/readest/readest/refs/heads/main/data/screenshots/dark_mode.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Reading with TTS speak out</caption>
      <image type="source">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/readest/readest/refs/heads/main/data/screenshots/tts_speak_aloud.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Reading tools with Wikipedia integration</caption>
      <image type="source">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/readest/readest/refs/heads/main/data/screenshots/wikipedia_vertical.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1">
    <content_attribute id="social-info">moderate</content_attribute>
  </content_rating>

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#d97706</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#b45309</color>
  </branding>
</component>
